A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Scholar in Residence, Office Files of Sadako Ogata FA1727
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Scholar in Residence, Office Files of Sadako Ogata
2000-2003
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ogata, Sadako N.
Ford Foundation
FA1727
1.23 Cubic Feet 3 Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files of Sadako Ogata who, from between 2001 and 2003, served as Ford Foundation Scholar in Residence. It consists of one series of subject files that document Ogata's work as Co-Chair of the United Nations Commission on Human Security (CHS) and as a leader in the broader international peace and governance field.
In addition to human security, Ogata's involvement and communication with scholars, professionals, and organizations interested in diplomacy and international assistance generally focused on the topics of refugees, children, and assistance to Afghanistan during this time period. Much of Ogata's communications, scheduling, and commitment making was moderated through her two assistants: Personal Assistant Megumi Nakamura, based in Tokyo, Japan and Executive Administrative Assistant Claudia Fletcher, based in New York, New York. Materials in the collection that Nakamura and Fletcher created, maintained, and distributed include correspondence, purchase records, and schedules.
In addition to the aforementioned materials, the collection also contains drafts, reports, planning notes, talking points written by Ogata for meetings, meeting agendas, copies of remarks made by Ogata, press releases, and publications.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:188.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 2000-2003
Biographical / Historical
Sadako Ogata (1927-2019) was a diplomat and academic who served as the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees between 1991 and 2000. She was a Scholar in Residence at the Ford Foundation between 2001 and 2003 whilst she also co-chaired the Commission on Human Security (CHS) and served as Special Representative of the Prime Minister of Japan on Afghanistan Assistance.
Ogata's academic positions included teaching and administrative jobs at the International Christian University (1965-1979) and Sophia University (1980-1991). Her diplomatic work started in 1976 when she worked as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary for the permanent mission of Japan to the United Nations. She also served as Chairman for the Executive Board of the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) between 1978 and 1979. Ogata served as UN High Commissioner for Refugees during a period of numerous refugee crises such as the Gulf War, the Yugoslav Wars, and the Rwandan genocide.
Following her time as Scholar in Residence at the Ford Foundation, Ogata continued her involvement with the UN. She served as the Chair of the Advisory Board on Human Security which was established on the recommendations put forth by the Commission on Human Security that she had co-chaired, and between 2006 and 2007, she served as a member of the Advisory Committee on Genocide Prevention. During this time, she also worked as President of the Japan International Cooperation Agency (JICA).
Ogata was born Sadako Nakamura on September 16, 1927. She earned a B.A. in English Literature from the University of the Sacred Heart in 1951, an M.A. in International Relations from Georgetown University in 1953, and a Ph.D. in Political Science from the University of California at Berkeley in 1963. Throughout her career, she was a member of numerous international peace and governance organizations including the Council of Foreign Relations, the International Committee of the Red Cross, the Global Coalition for Africa, the Trilateral Commission, the Schwab Foundation for Social Entrepreneurship, and the Foundation for the Refugee Education Trust. Her awards and honors include the Japanese Order of Culture, the Commander of the Legion d'honneur, and the Indira Gandhi Prize among others.
Related Materials
Documents pertaining to the UN Commission on Human Security which Sadako Ogata co-chaired can be found in the first two series of the Peter F. Geithner papers: FA1408, Peter F. Geithner papers
Ford Foundation; Refugees; Peace; International cooperation
- Subject files, 2000-2003; 1; 1.23 Cubic Feet 2 LTR and 1 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files Sadako Ogata created when she served as Scholar in Residence at the Ford Foundation from between 2001 and 2003. Files document Ogata's work as Co-Chair of the United Nations Commission on Human Security (CHS) as well as her involvement in the larger international peace and governance field.
  Most of the files regarding the CHS appear to have been created in the context of its Third Meeting in June 2002 in Stockholm, Sweden. Nevertheless, these files and other ones in the series also contain materials that document the earlier history of the commission such as press releases announcing the formation of the CHS. Other records pertaining to the commission include correspondence, drafts, reports, talking points Ogata wrote for meetings, meeting agendas, and planning notes. They show how the CHS sought to organize itself, select candidates for commissioners, and research literature on human security.
  Other documents in the series provide evidence of Ogata's involvement with organizations and projects focusing on subjects such as refugees, children, and assistance to Afghanistan. Ogata served as Special Representative of the Prime Minister of Japan on Afghanistan Assistance during this time period. Much of Ogata's communication with scholars, professionals, and organizations concerned with international peace and governance was handled by Megumi Nakamura, her Personal Assistant based in Tokyo, Japan and by Claudia Fletcher, her Executive Administrative Assistant based in New York, New York. Correspondence, purchase records, and schedules created, maintained, and distributed by Nakamura and Fletcher document the communications Ogata had with different individuals and organizations as well as the meetings and conferences she attended.
  - Commission on Human Security (CHS) Third Meeting, Stockholm, Sweden, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence and speeches and statements by Ogata, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - United Nations Special Session on Children, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Commission on Human Security (CHS), 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Human Security Network Meeting, Santiago, Chile, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Commission on Human Security (CHS) Third Meeting Report/Draft chapter on Great Lakes Region of Africa, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Foundation for Microprojects in Vietnam, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Commission on Human Security (CHS) Third Meeting, Stockholm, Sweden, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - European correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Megumi Nakamura, Personal Assistant - Communications and scheduling, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
  - Schwab Foundation for Global Entrepreneurship, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)